Mazel tov מזל טוב, Mazel Tov, shana tova שנה טובה, Shana Tova,
year of 5773, should be a good year for all of us
and an easy fast for everyone today.
We pick up with Mem-Chet amud aleph
מ"ח עמוד א', Mem-Chet Amud Aleph, Amar Rav Yehuda אמר רב יהודה,
Amar Rav Yehuda, and we had just had yesterday very important Gemara
גמרא Gemara about you know the issue about count who can count
questions about counting a minor for the tenth of a minyan מנין
minyan and I mentioned other discussions that come up in Tosfos תוספות
Tosfos that maybe the same should be true for a woman as
the tenth for a minyan מנין, minyan, questions to pask פסק pask
like that Gemara גמרא, Gemara, the idea of a minor holding onto
a Sefer Torah ספר תורה Sefer Torah which is raised in Tosfos
תוספות, Tosfos, major debates around this issue about are there different standards
for the question about who is number ten. Anyway the Gemara גמרא
Gemara now so that was very important for both halachot הלכות halachot
which came up a great deal in various communities which really struggled
with minyanim מניינים minyanim but now we move on to the basic
issues of what constitutes a zimmun זימון zimmun and this is also
a very relevant and daily halacha הלכה. halacha. So picking up from
Mem-Chet amud aleph מ"ח עמוד א', Mem-Chet Amud Aleph, two dots, about
ten lines down, Amar Rav Yehuda אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda
said Rav Yehuda brei de-Rav Shmuel bar Shilat בריה דרב שמואל בר
שילת brei de-Rav Shmuel bar Shilat mishmei de-Rav משמיה דרב mishmei de-Rav
in the name of Rav, tisha achlu dagan ve-echad achal yerak תשעה
אכלו דגן ואחד אכל ירק, tisha achlu dagan ve-echad achal yerak, nine
people ate grain and one person ate vegetable, so meaning let's say
they didn't all eat bread, so this is again the requirement of
ten for Eloheinu אלהינו Eloheinu in the zimmun זימון, zimmun, so mitzstarfin
מצטרפין mitzstarfin so
that he can count that number ten. Now again this does parallel
some of the discussions yesterday about maybe an infant counting, even a
child, an infant counting for number ten, again as I said a
minute ago questions whether we accept or reject that Gemara גמרא, Gemara,
here it says that the person is an adult but ate veg
you know ate vegetable did not eat bread, at least he ate
something. So Amar Rav Zeira אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, so
Rav Zeira baei minei mei-Rav Yehuda בעי מיניה מרב יהודה baei minei
mei-Rav Yehuda so I asked from Rav Yehuda, so this so shemona
mahu שמונה מהו, shemona mahu, shiva mahu שבעה מהו, shiva mahu, what
about eight, what about seven, you know how many do you really
need to eat bread? Amar lei אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
to me lo shna לא שנא lo shna it doesn't matter it's
that's fine same thing. Shisha vadai lo mibaia li ששה ודאי לא
מיבעיא לי shisha vadai lo mibaia li but I didn't ask or
vai de-lo mibaia li וואי דלא מיבעיא לי vai de-lo mibaia li
which fits better, woe that I didn't ask him about six, okay
because I should have checked I should have asked him about six,
I didn't ask him about that. So amar lei Rav Yirmiya אמר
ליה רב ירמיה amar lei Rav Yirmiya so Rav Yirmiya said shapir
avadt de-lo mibaia lach
שפיר עבדת דלא מיבעיא לך, shapir avadt de-lo mibaia lach,
it's good that you didn't ask, why did you need to ask
about six? Hasam tama mai ta'ama mishum de-ika ruba התם טעמא מאי
משום דאיכא רובא, hasam tama mai ta'ama mishum de-ika ruba, why did
he tell you nine eight and seven were okay because at least
the majority ate bread? Hacha nami ika ruba הכא נמי איכא רובא
hacha nami ika ruba so why should six be any different it's
also the
majority. But Rav Zeira that didn't ask and was bemoaning the fact
that he didn't ask so he held ruba de-minchar ba'ina רובא דמינכר
בעינא, ruba de-minchar ba'ina, no maybe there's a difference between seven and
six, seven is an obvious majority, six is just barely a majority,
so maybe you need an obvious majority to count as enough to
have eaten bread to say Eloheinu אלהינו Eloheinu and actually that's how
we rule that if you have seven that ate bread you can
say Eloheinu אלהינו Eloheinu if three did not, if three only ate
like vegetables but if you have six that ate bread you do
not say Eloheinu אלהינו. Eloheinu.
If they drink something
so yeah that's a discussion that Tosfos תוספות Tosfos has others have
but v'hacha hilchata והכי הלכתא v'hacha hilchata she-echad achal yerak o shata
kos yayin mitzstarfin שאחד אכל ירק או שתה כוס יין מצטרפין, she-echad
achal yerak o shata kos yayin mitzstarfin, okay. Ve-afilu nevarech Eloheinu yecholin
lomar ואפילו נברך אלהינו יכולין לומר ve-afilu nevarech Eloheinu yecholin lomar she-shitiya
bichlal achila ששתיה בכלל אכילה, she-shitiya bichlal achila, okay. Now the next
question that so he says yayin יין yayin okay so there's some
question. Now the next question that's not addressed in the Gemara גמרא
Gemara that needs to be is because say yesterday who counted as
the tenth seemed to be a lower standard than who counted as
the third for zimmun זימון, zimmun, so why is the Gemara גמרא
Gemara rejected the possibility that a minor counted as the third it
played with the possibility that a minor could count for the tenth.
So the question is what is the halacha הלכה halacha for the
third of the zimmun זימון zimmun and Tosfos תוספות Tosfos has two
opinions does the third if you only have three have to each
eat bread or not? Tosfos תוספות Tosfos does not conclude. In the
Shulchan Aruch שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch three opinions are brought down about
this, one says that all three have to eat bread for the
core three they all have to eat bread, and correct one says
it's enough that the third person eats mezonot מזונות mezonot and the
third opinion says even if the third person just eats some shehakol
שהכל shehakol some vegetables or
whatever that whatever yayin יין yayin and drinking anyway that's also fine.
So interestingly the Shulchan Aruch שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says if a
third person comes to join you you know like don't get into
a problem if he's not having bread don't let him eat anything.
Now sometimes you can't control that anyway he's hungry you're all sitting
down with your lunch at a table two people two people have
sandwiches the other person's got you know some vegetables or whatever they've
got some quiche who knows what, so the basic p'sak פסק p'sak
is is that if it happens you know that that then you
do a zimmun זימון zimmun even if the even if the third
person just has vegetables. Now that's particularly Tosfos תוספות Tosfos tends to
be a little more. more lenient about these things in general nowadays
because we don't have the זימון zimun of the גמרא Gemara where
somebody's מוציא motzi somebody else. Everybody is doing their own ברכת המזון.
Birkat Hamazon. So at the end of the day, the question is
really just about that introductory phrase, so also that leads to some
degree of more leniency around some of these issues. Now sometimes people
דווקא davka do it, right? There are two people eating and somebody
is there with them and they say, you know, eat a little
bit so we can have a זימון. zimun. So if you're דווקא
davka going out of your way, it seems, you know, better for
at least for the three, that the third person at least has
מזונות, mezonot, as I said there is even an opinion of המוציא.
Hamotzi.
But certainly you need at least two of them to have eaten
bread. Okay, so that is a very relevant and daily הלכה halacha
when it comes to issues of זימון, zimun, fascinatingly the גמרא Gemara
does not discuss the three, it only discusses the ten.
Okay, so you said that the three opinions in
practice, even if the third guy is kind of like, you know,
dragged along, we should try to have him have מזונות? mezonot?
What the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually says is have him have
המוציא Hamotzi and if not he shouldn't be eating or I mean
you should proactively try to—no, no, in practice, you know, I think
מזונות mezonot we say with, like, you know, we even will proactively
do it in my experience that people feel that at least for
מזונות, mezonot, come have a little מזונות mezonos so you can answer
to us to זימון zimun and so on.
And that's just like a קטן katan having מזונות? mezonot?
We're not dealing with קטן katan right now, okay, but with the—the
general פסק psak is that even if the person just had some
type of a vegetable or a שהכל shehakol or whatever, it doesn't
make a difference, that you can have them answer to זימון, zimun,
not lead the זימון. zimun. The person leading the זימון zimun should
obviously be one of the people that had the bread. And we'll
talk a little bit more about that in a minute. Okay, so
let's take a look now at the next גמרא. Gemara. ינאי מלכא
ומלכתא, Yannai Malka uMalchata, Yannai the king and the queen, okay, famous
story about King Yannai. What? Where are
you? ינאי מלכא ומלכתא כרכו ריפתא בהדי הדדי. Yannai Malka uMalchata kerichu
rifta bahadi hadadei. So they were sitting and having bread with one
another, not exactly clear how many other people were there, presumably there
were other people there, I don't know, we'll see. Okay,
now ומדקטלינהו לרבנן, umidekatlinhu lerabanan, since they had killed all the rabbis,
okay, story that Yannai the king basically there's a famous story in
the משנה בכורים Mishna Bikkurim or whatever other stories about Yannai that
anyway at a certain point he felt insulted by the rabbis and
he killed them all out.
So they had killed out all the rabbis, לא הוה ליה איניש
לברוכי להו, lo hava lei inish levoruchei lehu, so they had nobody
to lead the benching for them.
If only two together, counting?
Well, that's the question, were there other people there or was it
just him and his wife? It sounds like, we'll keep on reading,
it sounds like that there's more. Okay, but it only mentions him
and his wife.
I said they mentioned his wife.
Right, well she'll be part of the story in a minute. Okay,
let's keep on reading, let's keep on reading. Anyway, there was nobody
left to—there was nobody that could lead the benching for them. Nobody
perhaps knew the benching. So right, very firm about the benching, doesn't
matter about killing out all the rabbis but very firm about the
benching. Exactly. אמר לה לדביתהו, amar lah ledevitehu, so he said to
his wife, מאן יהב לן גברא דמברך לן, man yahav lan gavra
demeravech lan, who can find us a man to lead the benching
for us? So אמרה ליה, amrah lei, so she said to him,
אשתבע לי דאי מייתינא לך גברא דלא מצערת ליה, ishtava li dei
maitina lach gavra dela metza'arat lei, swear to me that if I
bring you somebody that can lead the benching,
that you won't give him a hard time. Okay, so אשתבע לה,
ishtava lah, he swore to her. אייתיא ליה לשמעון בן שטח, aytiah
lei leShimon ben Shetach, so she brought him Shimon ben Shetach, אחוה
הוה, achuvah havah, that was her brother. So she had managed to
hide away Shimon ben Shetach her brother from this purge of the
intelligentsia, from the purge of the rabbis. So אייתיא, aytiah, אותביה בין
דידיה לדידה, otveih bein didei ledidah, so they had him sit between
the king and the queen. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so Yannai said to him, חזי כמה יקרא עבדינן
לך, chazi kama yekara avdinan lach, look how much honor we're giving
you, we're bringing you to our table, we're sitting you between the
king and the queen. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to
him, לאו את מוקרת לי, lav at mokrat li, it's not you
that's giving me the honor, אלא אורייתא היא דמוקרא לי, ela oraita
hi demokra li, it's the Torah that affords me honor, דכתיב סלסליה
ותרוממך, dechativ salsaleha uteromemeka, if you will honor it, if you will
give it glory it will raise you up, תכבדך כי תחבקנה, techabedeka
ki techabkenah, it will give you honor when you embrace it. So
the honor I get is from the Torah, not from you. אמר
לה, amar lah, so then Yannai said to his wife, קחזי דלא
מקבל מרות, kachazi dela mekabel marut, look, I told you, this guy
isn't accepting my authority. So I tried to tell him I'm giving
him honor and he has to respond like that. Really wonder about
Shimon ben Shetach, but you
know okay anyway whether that was so self-preserved, how self-preserving he was
being with these statements.
Anyway, בירושלמי b'Yerushalmi when this is cited, Jim Singer or Ben-Yamina points
this out, which just gives you a little bit of context as
to why they're like so מקפיד makpid on benching is because there
was an instance beforehand where the פרסיים Parsiyim came and they knew
Shimon ben Shetach beforehand and he was there at another meal. So
they asked, oh where's that sage that you know was so smart,
what happened to him? So therefore Yannai was forced to kind of
bring him back. Okay, so that's the context for this.
Does she have a name somewhere? Don't we know
her?
שלומציון. Shlomtzion. שלומציון המלכה. Shlomtzion Hamalka. Okay. All right.
So יהבו ליה כסא לברוכי, yahavu lei kasa levoruchei, so they gave
him the cup to lead the benching. אמר *Amar*, so he said,
היכי אברך *heichi evarech*? What ברכה bracha *bracha* should I make? I
haven't eaten with them. They just brought me into the meal. I
haven't eaten anything with them. So ברוך שאכל ינאי וחבריו *Baruch she-achal
Yannai ve-chaverav*, and since I can't say נברך *nevareich*, I didn't eat,
so I should say, 'Blessed the one who ינאי *Yannai* and his
friends ate from.' So now his friends, you see, the other people
at the meal. Anyway, I can't say נברך *nevareich*, I haven't eaten.
So שפתיה לכסא *shasyei le-hu kassa*. So instead he drank the cup.
They gave him the cup to make ברכת המזון Birchath HaMazon. *Birkat
HaMazon* with, but he drank it. So that makes it as if
he would have eaten with them. So יהבו ליה כסא אחרינא *yahavu
lei kassa achrina*, so they refilled his cup. Okay, בריך *bareich*, now
he was able to בענטש *bentch* because he had drunk with them.
Okay, אמר *amar*, so now you see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before
spoke about eating vegetables, now talking about drinking wine, so maybe it
should be in the same category, but the difference here is that
he was leading the בענטשינג *bentching*. He wasn't just responding. So אמר
רבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא בר אבא *Amar Rabbi Abba breih de-Rabbi
Chiyya bar Abba*, so Rabbi Abba the son of Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba said, אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, in the
name of Rabbi Yochanan, of course that's the גירסא *girsa*, שמעון בן
שטח Shimon ben Shetach דעבד לגרמיה הוא דעבד *Shimon ben Shetach de-avad
legarmei hu de-avad*. What he did, he was doing for himself, meaning
he was פסקנינג *paskening* for himself, that's not the way we פסקן
paskened *pasken*. דהכי אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן *De-hachi
Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, this is what Rabbi
Chiyya bar Abba says in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, לעולם אינו
מוציא motzi. את הרבים ידי חובתן עד שיאכל כזית kezayit דגן *le-olam
eino motzi et harabbim yedei chovatan ad she-yochal kezayit dagan*. You cannot
do, you cannot discharge others from their responsibility until you've eaten bread.
So whether you might constitute one of the ten or one of
the three, depending on how many people you think were present, even
if you didn't eat bread, you can only lead the בענטשינג *bentching*.
Now leading again is because you are here being מוציא motzi *motzi*
them. Again, other people, again, their leading of the בענטשינג *bentching* was
that they were not actually doing, the other people were not doing
the בענטשינג *bentching* themselves. That's why they needed to bring in שמעון
בן שטח *Shimon ben Shetach*, because it wasn't just who can say
the first three lines. It's who knows the whole בענטשינג *bentching* to
lead the בענטשינג *bentching*. So you cannot be מוציא motzi *motzi* people
and lead the בענטשינג *bentching* until you've had bread. Now רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* pose here with a question, which is
that presumably here we say you have to eat a כזית kezayit.
*kezayit* of bread, but presumably which sounds like that would have been
okay if שמעון בן שטח *Shimon ben Shetach* had eaten a כזית
kezayit *kezayit*. But presumably ינאי *Yannai* and the queen and everybody else
was there, filled themselves up, had כדי שביעה *kedei sevi'ah*, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* elsewhere indicates that if you have a כזית kezayit.
*kezayit*, you're only a דרבנן d'rabanan, *derabbanan* obligation, it's only when you
actually are sated by the bread that you've eaten and the food
that you've eaten that it's a דאורייתא de'oraisa, *de-oraita* obligation. So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* have a whole serious question: how
could somebody who's eaten a כזית kezayit *kezayit* be מוציא *motzi* people
who have actually filled themselves up and have a דאורייתא de'oraisa *de-oraita*
obligation? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* seems to give an answer that says
maybe in some circumstances a דרבנן derabbanan *derabbanan* can be מוציא *motzi*
a דאורייתא de'oraisa *de-oraita* some of the time. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is
very, very upset about that. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* basically says another, like
another amazing answer, which is like shocking. He says, you know what?
You really can be מוציא *motzi* somebody else in בענטשינג *bentching* even
if you haven't eaten. You can't make a ברכה ראשונה Bracha Rishona:
*bracha rishona* if you're not going to derive benefit, but to make
בענטשינג *bentching*, he says the same way I can be מוציא *motzi*
you with a ברכה bracha *bracha* even if I'm already יוצא yotza.
*yotzei*, I could be מוציא *motzi* you. So even if I haven't
eaten, I can be מוציא *motzi*, which is a bizarre idea. The
difference is that I was in the category, I became obligated, I
was יוצא *yotzei*, like if I already read מגילה *Megillah*, I already
heard שופר *shofar*, and now I can still do it for you.
But בענטשינג *bentching*, you would say is if in this circumstance I
haven't eaten, how could my בענטשינג *bentching* at all be meaningful? I
haven't right now eaten. But תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says in principle you
could. And the only reason you have to eat is so that
you could say the words נברך שאכלנו משלו nevarech she-achalnu mi-shelo. *nevareich
she-achalnu mi-shelo*. But it's only because you have to say שאכלנו משלו
she-achalnu mi-shelo? *she-achalnu mi-shelo* that you have to have eaten. But technically
you could be מוציא *motzi* somebody else even if you haven't eaten.
And that's why שמעון בן שטח *Shimon ben Shetach* can lead. This
leads to a lot of interesting discussions in the פוסקים poskim *Poskim*,
which means is that really true? Meaning, so let's say you don't
have to say נברך שאכלנו משלו *nevareich she-achalnu mi-shelo*. For example, let's
say we're not in a זימון zimmun, *zimun*. Let's say it's just
me and you and you're not in a state to בענטש *bentch*,
you don't know the text, maybe you've drunk a little too much
to drink, you're a little drunk now, whatever it is. Can I
actually make a בענטשינג *bentching* for you if I haven't eaten? Is
that what we really are meant to believe? So some פוסקים *Poskim*
say yeah, that's what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says, but others really object
to that. So this really leads to a lot of interesting discussion:
why can the person who ate a כזית kezayit *kezayit* be מוציא
*motzi* somebody who's had his fill? And the בה"ג Ba-hag *Behag* in
הלכות גדולות *Halachot Gedolot* actually פסקן *paskens* he cannot. When the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says a כזית kezayit *kezayit* can be מוציא *motzi* others,
it means if they've had a כזית kezayit. *kezayit*. But if somebody
has had his fill and somebody else has had a כזית *kezayit*,
it's only the person who had his fill can be מוציא *motzi*
other people because that is a דאורייתא d'oraita, *de-oraita* obligation and the
כזית *kezayit* is the דרבנן *derabbanan*. Now, one final point about this,
which is again that nowadays the standards tend to be a little
bit more, like, sort of inclusive because we're not really tend not
to be מוציא *motzi* other people in our בענטשינג *bentching*. Nowadays our
זימון zimmun, *zimun* is just that introductory stuff and then everybody בענטשעס
*bentches* for themselves. So nowadays people are not so מקפיד *makpid*: I've
had a כזית *kezayit*, you filled yourself up, I can lead the
בענטשינג *bentching* because all I'm really doing is saying the opening lines.
And anyway, mostly that's how the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* read this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But at a time when
you were מוציא *motzi* other people, this led to a lot of
very heated debate about is this really true that the דרבנן *derabbanan*,
the person who had the כזית *kezayit*, can discharge the obligation of
the person who had their fill,
the
דאורייתא d'oraita.
*de-oraita*? coercion?
Well, that might be what the גמרא Gemara meant when he said
he was acting for himself. It might not even mean that under
other circumstances maybe שמעון בן שטח wouldn't have פסקן that either. In
those circumstances, he allowed himself to rely on the idea that at
least he had something to drink. Okay, so that's possibly what the
גמרא Gemara even means, that he did it for himself.
So, but this is brought in conjunction with this תשעה אכל ירק
ואחד אכל ירק. tisha achal yarak ve-chad achal yarak. So, how does
תוספות Tosafos say that you don't have to eat anything if the
גמרא Gemara is saying that you at least have to eat something,
right? תשעה דגמא ואחד אכל ירק. tisha dagma ve-echad achal yarak.
I understand. תוספות Tosafos is saying in order for the institution of
זימון, zimmun that's where we might need the leader to be תשעה
דגמא tisha dagma on other people, to be דגמא dagma on other
things, because others say נברך שאכלנו משלו. But that's for the institution
of זימון, zimmun, not for the institution to be מוציא. That's what
תוספות says. But again, this is heavily debated.
Yeah, go ahead.
So why are we talking about the word שאכלנו משלו? So change
it to שאכלו משלו. she-achalu mi-shelo.
Well, but he said what should I say? שאכל ינאי וחבריו משלו?
she-achal Yanai ve-chaveirav mi-shelo?
Why not? I don't know, it's a good point. Well, partly it's
because, you know, what's the
פסוק pasuk the גמרא Gemara quotes? במקום שבשבחו יחדיו, be-makom she-be-shivcho yachdav,
that there has to be the institution was created as some type
of a joint way of praising. So we're all participating in that
praise, you know. So, and we're equal participants, aren't we?
If I remember my הלכה halacha correctly.
Right, so they say ברוך ומבורך. baruch u-mevorach. Right, we had that
before. But again, this is the institution of זימון zimmun, that the
rabbis created, which is a sense of everybody being sort of participant
in this and equally thanking. But you're right. Anyway, תוספות's answer is
strange from many
perspectives. And פוסקים largely... whatever, I don't know. But anyway, you know,
the בה"ג Ba-hag is the more comfortable answer, but it doesn't fit
the circumstances as much. The בה"ג says that when it says you
ate a כזית it's enough, it means everybody else had a כזית.
But if other people had their fill, that would actually make the
story different.
Even if I had a כביצה? kabeitzah?
What, we'll talk soon, כזית כביצה kabeitzah same. Okay. So anyway, but
that now, by the way, just to remind, just to sort of
sum up the הלכה, halacha, so again, the הלכה halacha is that
if you want people to count for the מנין minyan for ten,
only seven have to eat bread. If you want them to count
for the three for the זימון, Zimmun, ideally the third one should
at least have מזונות, mezonot, but בדיעבד be-diavat even if they had
other types of stuff, the third guy. But the people that lead
should be the person who's eaten bread. And ideally, based on the
discussion I just made to you, if there's somebody who's had their
fill, ideally that should be the person that leads, but really we
allow anybody that had a כזית. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
איתמר נמי, itmar nami, so we saw similarly. Did I skip a
line? Yes, I skipped a line.
מתיבי, meitvei, I'll ask you on this. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, עלה והסיב עמהם, alah ve-heseiv imahem, if
somebody went up
and reclined with
them, אפילו לא טבל עמהם אלא בציר, afilu lo taval imahem ela
be-tzir, even if he only did a dipping into the vinegar, into
the brine or whatever, meaning he didn't have a big meal, he
just dipped a little bit, ולא אכל עמהם אלא גרוגרת אחת מצטרף,
ve-lo achal imahem ela grogeret achat mitztareif, and even if he only
ate with them a גרוגרת, grogeret, which is a pressed, what is
it? A fig, a
pressed fig, אחת מצטרף, achat mitztareif, he can join. So presumably it
sounds
like even if you had a vegetable, you can lead, this is
how he's reading it. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מצטרף מצטרף, mitztareif mitztareif, you can be part of the ten or
the three if that's debated, but anyway,
להוציא את הרבים ידי חובתם עד שיאכל כזית דגן. le-hotzi et ha-rabbim
yedei chovatam ad she-yochal kezayit dagan. But in order to be the
one that leads and is מוציא the people, you have to have
actually eaten the כזית worth of bread.
איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was also thought, אמר רב חנא בר
יהודה משמיה דרבא, amar Rav Chana bar Yehuda mi-shmei de-Rava, אפילו לא
טבל עמהם אלא בציר, afilu lo taval imahem ela be-tzir, מ"ח עמוד
ב', mem-chet amud bet, even if he only dipped in the brine,
ולא אכל עמהם אלא גרוגרת אחת מצטרף, ve-lo achal imahem ela grogeret
achat mitztareif, you
can be part of the group, again, definitely the ten, maybe
the three, ולהוציא את הרבים ידי חובתם אינו מוציא עד שיאכל כזית
דגן, ve-le-hotzi et ha-rabbim yedei chovatam eino motzi ad she-yochal kezayit dagan,
only until you've actually had a כזית of bread.
אמר רב חנא בר יהודה משמיה דרבא, amar Rav Chana bar Yehuda
mi-shmei de-Rava, הלכתא, hilcheta, the הלכה halacha is, אכל עלה ירק ושתה
כוס של יין מצטרף, achal aleh yerek ve-shatah kos shel yayin mitztareif,
even if he had just a leaf of a vegetable or he
drank a cup of wine,
מצטרף, mitztareif, you can
combine, but להוציא אינו מוציא עד שיאכל כזית דגן, le-hotzi eino motzi
ad she-yochal kezayit dagan, like we said, you cannot be מוציא until
you've had a כזית of bread. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman,
so now we are now that we've had a lot of discussion
about what constitutes a זימון, zimmun. we're finally turning to the actual
text of the בנצ'ן bentching itself.
משה תיקן לישראל ברכת הזן, Moshe tikken le-Yisrael birkat ha-zan, משה Moshe
was the one that established the ברכה bracha of הזן את הכל,
ha-zan et ha-kol, okay, because you could say
על הארץ ועל המזון, al ha-aretz ve-al ha-mazon, at least you could
say, you know, ואכלת ושבעת וברכת את ה' אלהיך, ve-achalta ve-savata u-veirachta
et Hashem Elokecha, so at least for the thanking which is in
the Torah, at least the thanking for the food משה Moshe could
do, but he wasn't, he couldn't say על הארץ ועל המזון. al
ha-aretz ve-al ha-mazon. Because they hadn't yet come into
ישראל. Israel. בשעה שירד להם המן, Bish'as sheyerad lahem haman, so when
the מן man came, he said you should all say the ברכה
bracha of
הזן את הכל. hazan es hakol. יהושע תיקן להם ברכת הארץ. Yehoshua
tikken lahem birchas ha'aretz. יהושע Yehoshua established the ברכה bracha of על
הארץ ועל המזון al ha'aretz v'al hamazon because that was when they
were in the land.
כיון שנכנסו לארץ ישראל Kivan shenichnesu l'Eretz Yisrael or משנכנסו mishenichnesu when
they came into the land, now you could say על הארץ ועל
המזון. al ha'aretz v'al hamazon.
By the way, could you imagine what a thrill that had to
be for יהושע? Yehoshua? Just imagine, משה Moshe couldn't do this and
יהושע Yehoshua could! Right, it had to be most extraordinary, and we're
just talking, but to be there,
it had to
be the most extraordinary moment.
Why? Because now you're able to fulfill this biblical מצוה mitzvah that
you couldn't fulfill before, right? Right? Thank you, absolutely. Yeah.
Yes. So he didn't... now, I will also say by the way,
you know ספרדים Sefardim have the נוסח, nusach, some of the נוסח
nusach in the first ברכה bracha you say
ככתוב פותח את ידך ומשביע לכל חי רצון. ka-katuv poseach es yadecha
umasbia l'chol chai ratzon. So the רשב"א Rashba says in a תשובה,
teshuvah, it's a little hard to understand how you have that נוסח
nusach if we're supposed to understand that משה Moshe established the ברכה
bracha because that פסוק pasuk wasn't written yet in the time of
משה. Moshe. All right, so anyway, that raises some questions about that
נוסח. nusach. Maybe a little bit of רוח הקודש. ruach hakodesh. All
right, maybe.
Anyway, this idea that he established this about הזן לכל, hazan l'chol,
but he talks about הזן את הכל, hazan es hakol, and he
talks about really natural and everybody gets, not everybody got מן, man,
only the בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Right. It's a little reminiscent of
the question of what ברכה bracha do you make on the מן?
man?
Right, but your point being that the same way the מן man
came straight from God,
I would have, if I were making a ברכה bracha, on מן
man it would be something about the miraculous nature of it, right?
But maybe the idea is supposed to be that the miraculous makes
us aware of the miracles that are part of the natural order
as well, you know, that nature provides, that's also הזן את הכל.
hazan es hakol. Nature provides, יהושע Yehoshua didn't know the הזן את
הכל hazan es hakol part?
I don't know.
Anyway, so that's what יהושע Yehoshua said. Now,
דוד ושלמה תיקנו בונה ירושלים. David u'Shlomo tiknu boneh Yerushalayim. Now here's
the question, right? How do we have a ברכה bracha בונה ירושלים?
boneh Yerushalayim? So that seems like it's post-חורבן. churban. But the גמרא
Gemara understands, because as we're going to see in a minute, understands
that it's דאורייתא, d'oraita. but similar to the way that הארץ ha'aretz
was דאורייתא d'oraita. but couldn't be said until there was a land
to say it
about, so בונה ירושלים, boneh Yerushalayim, the גמרא Gemara is going to
indicate later it understands to be דאורייתא de'oraita but couldn't be said
until there was a built ירושלים Yerushalayim that it was something to
praise with. So בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim doesn't have to mean it's
destroyed, even if it currently is built, God is the one that
had built it, that helped us, create, come to ירושלים Yerushalayim and
build up the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so it's sort of an
active verb. God is constantly בונה ירושלים, boneh Yerushalayim, not like it's
not so right now.
דוד תיקן על ישראל עמך ועל ירושלים עירך. David tikken al Yisrael
amcha v'al Yerushalayim irecha. דוד David had the part about ישראל Yisrael
and ירושלים Yerushalayim because דוד David at least established ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ושלמה
תיקן על הבית הגדול והקדוש, u'Shlomo tikken al habayis hagadol vehakadosh, on
the holy house, because it was שלמה Shlomo that built the house,
so that part wasn't added until שלמה. Shlomo. הטוב והמטיב, HaTov VeHaMeitiv,
now that ברכה, bracha הטוב והמטיב, HaTov VeHaMeitiv, ביבנה תיקנוה. b'Yavne tiknuha.
That was in יבנה Yavne after the, after this event about the
בר כוכבא Bar Kochba revolt when finally they had all these people
that were murdered and they allowed them to be buried. And then
they made the ברכה bracha of הטוב והמטיב, HaTov VeHaMeitiv, כנגד הרוגי
ביתר, kineged harugei Beitar, opposite those who had died in ביתר Beitar
that they were given over to burial, as we said yesterday. Originally
that ברכה bracha was very short: ברוך ה' הטוב והמטיב. Baruch Hashem
hatov vehameitiv. That was it, just like we say הטוב והמטיב hatov
vehameitiv now, became a whole paragraph later and we'll see more about
that in a little bit later. What exactly it's doing in בענטשן
bentsching is also not so clear. Maybe it's just that בענטשן bentsching
is all these different ways we bless השם, Hashem, so we added
this, but also obviously there's an interesting juxtaposition about that with בונה
ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim in a post-חורבן churban era. Anyway, אמר רב מתנא,
amar Rav Matna, because רב מתנא Rav Matna said, אותו היום שניתנו
הרוגי ביתר לקבורה, oso hayom shenitnu harugei Beitar l'kvura, the day that
those that were murdered in ביתר Beitar were allowed to be buried,
תיקנו ביבנה הטוב והמטיב. tiknu b'Yavne hatov vehameitiv. They established in יבנה
Yavne הטוב והמטיב. HaTov VeHaMeitiv. Okay, הטוב שלא הסריחו, hatov shelo hisrichu,
God is good that the bodies did not spoil, did not become
rancid, והמטיב שניתנו לקבורה, vehameitiv shenitnu l'kvura,
and God was good to others that he actually allowed that the
bodies were given over to be buried. It's not exactly clear to
me why one is הטוב hatov and the other's המטיב, hameitiv, in
both of them it's God doing good for others, but anyway. But
what?
That's a pretty gory kind of reasoning for הטוב והמטיב. hatov vehameitiv.
I know.
Normal right?
Beautiful thing.
So as I was saying, maybe I said it in too much
too shortly before, הטוב והמטיב hatov vehameitiv is like a real ברכה
bracha of שמחה. simcha. Halachically it's even more powerful than
שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. שהחיינו shehecheyanu is something good for you, הטוב והמטיב hatov
vehameitiv is that others benefit as well, although people like שהחיינו shehecheyanu
better because it's a nice... the נוסח nusach is... הטוב והמטיב hatov
vehameitiv is over before it begins. But anyway, halachically הטוב והמטיב hatov
vehameitiv is a more important
ברכה bracha and it could be that in the context of post-חורבן
churban where בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim is, you know, the ירושלים Yerushalayim
that is currently destroyed, it's not the בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim as
the גמרא Gemara mentioned in the time of דוד David and שלמה,
Shlomo, you know, there's also a sense here of the sort of...
Finding the positive even in a state of exile. So you know
it's sort of like the כשם שמברכין על הטוב כך מברכין על
הרע, keshem shemevarchin al hatov kach mevarchin al hara, so it's not
exactly מברכין על הרע, mevarchin al hara, but that right now you
know we're not ideal. We don't have the land. I mean in
the times of the גמרא Gemara obviously now it's different. We don't
have the land, we don't have ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's destroyed. You know,
but there's a sense of still even הטוב והמטיב, Hatov VeHameitiv, seeing
God's goodness even in this sort of post-exilic period.
Even when they were killed. Right. To saying to God thank you
that we can that their bodies are and that we can bury
them. Right. Still they were killed.
I understand, I understand. That's the point I'm making. That after saying
בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim it underscores on the one hand it's all
about thanking God and the way the benching is set up, thanking
God for הארץ הטובה Ha'aretz Hatovah and they don't have הארץ הטובה.
Ha'aretz Hatovah. They're in exile, right? And thanking for ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they
don't have ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's destroyed. So in a way הטוב והמטיב
Hatov VeHameitiv is saying even in the context of no Israel, you
know no land, no בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, people have been killed
in exile, we still find ways to thank God. That's the point
that I'm saying is exactly that context.
It's almost a parallel with קדיש. Kaddish. Right.
I mean we're in deep
mourning and everything seems destroyed in our lives but we are
צידוק הדין Tzidduk Hadin we're praising. Right. But that's a little more
like a צידוק הדין. Tzidduk Hadin. That's a more immediate sort of
acknowledging God's sort of in the bad itself. Here I'm saying a
little different is finding the good, you know being able to focus
on those things that are good even in a larger context of
exile when things are bad. And I think specifically about the benching
which all relates to a time when we're supposed to be in
the land, right? And we're supposed to have the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. So that's the way I understand it. All right. So now
the גמרא Gemara says: תנו רבנן: Tanoo Rabbanan: סדר ברכת המזון כך
היא. Seder Birchath HaMazon kach hee. Here actually is the order of
ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon ברכה bracha ראשונה: ברכת הזן. Birchath HaZan. The
first one is הזן את הכל. Hazan es hakol. We're skipping the
זימון, ברכת הזימון. Birchath HaZimmun. שנייה: Shniya: ברכת הארץ, Birchath Ha'Aretz, על
הארץ ועל המזון, al ha'aretz ve'al hamazon, the land. שלישית: Shlishi: בונה
ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim, build Jerusalem. רביעית: Revii: הטוב והמטיב. Hatov VeHameitiv. Okay,
that's pretty straightforward.
ובשבת, U'be-Shabbos, on שבת, Shabbos, מתחיל בנחמה ומסיים בנחמה ואומר קדושת היום
באמצע. matchil be-nechama u-mesayem be-nechama ve-omer kedushas hayom be-emtza. So you begin
with נחמה. Nechama. רש״י Rashi says it means you start like the
normal נוסח הברכה nussach abracha in the beginning like which is רחם
Rachem which is the way the third ברכה bracha of ירושלים Yerushalayim
ends. You end with בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim which is a fourth
source of נחמה. Nechama. So basically the way רש״י Rashi reads this
is you begin and end with the standard נוסח הברכה nussach abracha
and you stick in the middle the fact that it is שבת.
Shabbos. תוספות has some that actually would change the whole נוסח הברכה
nussach abracha on שבת. Shabbos. If you take a look at תוספות
he
says the word מתחילין matchilin בנחמה be-nechama but the line is about
six lines down it says מתחילין בנחמנו וחותמין
בנחמת ציון עירך ובנין ירושלים. matchilin be-nachamenu ve-chosmin be-nechamat Tziyon ircha u-vinyan
Yerushalayim. So they actually change the נוסח הברכה nussach abracha on שבת
Shabbos to say console us. ונותנין טעם לדבריהם דרחם הוי לשון תחינה
ואין אומרים תחנונים בשבת. Ve-nosnin ta'am le-divreihem de-rachem havei lashon techina ve-ein
omrim tachanunim be-Shabbos. You can't say רחם. Rachem. That's a request. So
תוספות then תוספות rejects it. He says נחם nacham is also a
request. It's not different than רחם. Rachem. Okay. But anyway there were
some that actually took this גמרא Gemara that נחמה Nechama that somehow
you use a different text for the whole third ברכה bracha. on
שבת. Shabbos. But רש״י Rashi and תוספות say no, he means just
that you have the beginning and end the normal and you stick
in שבת Shabbos in the middle.
Must you begin benching with that though?
No. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: רצה לאומרה בנחמה אומרה. ratza
le-omra be-nechama omra. If you want to say it in ירושלים Yerushalayim
you can mention שבת Shabbos in בונה ירושלים. Boneh Yerushalayim. בברכת הארץ
אומרה, Be-birchath ha'aretz omra, if you want to say it in the
second ברכה bracha you can say it. בברכה שהתקינו חכמים ביבנה אומרה,
Be-bracha she-hitkinu chachamim be-Yavne omra, if you want to say it in
הטוב והמטיב Hatov VeHameitiv you can say it. Interesting. But not in
הזן את הכל. Hazan es hakol. Actually we ask ourselves right why
is what's the relevance of שבת Shabbos to the בונה ירושלים? Boneh
Yerushalayim? I mean why specifically there? I mean maybe because it ties
into the idea of the קרבנות korbanos sort of like the מוסף
Musaf you know and therefore. But ultimately what's it really שייך shayach
to specifically בונה ירושלים? Boneh Yerushalayim? So he says you know you
could put it in any but even when he says any he
doesn't say the first. Presumably the first is like the foundation and
you don't want to sort of fiddle with the first ברכה bracha
like we know in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei we add the insertions
other than עשרת ימי תשובה Aseret Yemei Teshuva which was heavily debated
in the Geonic period right we don't make insertions in the first
three ברכות. brachot. The changes we sort of make come in the
middle. Okay. So here too he was more flexible. He said the
first one no but really you could put it in any ברכה.
bracha Why should we do this benching at all though?
Well that's a general issue about אומר omer that's a good question
right why do we say it? But you know why does שבת
Shabbos so you know why is what does ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
have to do with שחרית? Shacharis? Okay. So there's a general idea
of כל יום תן לו מעין ברכותיו. kol yom tein lo me-ein
birchosav. You know you know that every day we sort of acknowledge
give you know sort of acknowledge what the as you know the
relevance of the day should be expressed in our תפילות. tefillot. Should
be expressed in the way we bless God. Somehow that should come
through. So even when it's not central like in מוסף Musaf so
obviously the idea that it's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is central. But
even when it's not central it's it forms a part of our
ברכות brachot of the way in which we sort of acknowledge and
thank God as we as we also are aware of what's special
about today and that's expressed in how
we already do that in תפילה? tefillah?
Yeah. So it's not an idea that once you said שבת Shabat
so I don't know and get it. I mention ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh in... שחרית *Shacharit*, why do I have to mention it in
מנחה *Mincha*, right? It's not like I mentioned it sometime today, but
anytime I am sort of, you know, in a serious sort of,
you know, now not everything, my ברכות brachot. השחר *Birchos Hashachar* I
don't say it. But you know, ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon *Birchas Hamazon*
and שמנה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei* are like these sort of probably like
these major תפילות *Tfillos* in the sense that they're multiple ברכות brachos.
*Brachos* and they're focused on, you know, one is focused on thanking
God, the other is focused on, you know, on both thanking and
praising and making requests. So those are like the core, like the
weightiest תפילות *Tfillos* of the day and that's where the special aspects
of the day get reflected are in those ברכות *Brachos*, in those
תפילות *Tfillos*. There is questions about when is it מעכב *Me'akev*? So
it's an interesting point that in שמנה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei*, most of
the time all those special things we say are מעכב *Me'akev* except
for not על הניסים *Al HaNissim* but the יעלה ויבא *Ya'aleh V'yavo*
part or whatever. But by benching it's usually only מעכב *Me'akev* if
you have to if the nature of the day requires you to
have a meal. Okay, so that also adds a point to this
which is is that if you're ob— if the day obligates you
to have a meal, then it has— then it very much is
connected to the idea of benching and then if you don't say
it you have to go back.
Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, חכמים אומרים
אינו אומר אלא בנחמה בלבד *Chachamim omrim eino omer ela benechama bilvad*
you can only say it in the נחמה *Nechama* in the third
ברכה bracha *Bracha*. חכמים היינו תנא קמא *Chachamim hainu Tanna Kamma* isn't
that the first opinion? איכא בינייהו דיעבד *Ika beinihu de'avad*. No, they
say only meaning that even if you by accident did it in
another one it does not count. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: מנין
minayin, לברכת המזון מן התורה *Minayin l'birkat hamazon min haTorah*? So that's
the basic structure. Now in the course of that we mentioned משה,
יהושע, דוד Dovid ושלמה *Moshe, Yehoshua, David U'Shlomo*. Maybe you would think
that only the first ברכה bracha *Bracha* is דאורייתא de'oraita *De'oraita*, that
was משה *Moshe*. Now we're going to show the idea in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about which parts of it are understood to be
דאורייתא de'oraita, *De'oraita*.
How do you know the idea of ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon *Birkat
Hamazon* from the תורה Torah *Torah*? שנאמר shene'emar, *Shene'emar*, it says, ואכלת
ושבעת וברכת v'achalta v'savata u'verachta. *V'achalta V'savata U'verachta*. Okay, eaten, satisfied, and
you bless. זו ברכת הזן *Zu Birkat Hazan*. So blessing is הזן
את הכל *Hazan et hakol*. את ה' אלהיך *Et Hashem Elokecha*, Hashem
your God, זו ברכת הזימון *Zu Birkat Hazimun*. So a little out
of order but that's what we get out of the פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk*. את ה' אלהיך *Et Hashem Elokecha* right is when is the
idea you declare God's name, you know, כי שם ה' אקרא ki
shem Hashem ekra הבו גודל לאלהינו *Ki shem Hashem ekra havu godel
l'Elokeinu*. So you call out like let's bless God and people respond.
So the sort of introduction and calling everybody to recognize God, that
is learned from את ה' אלהיך *Et Hashem Elokecha*. על הארץ ha'aretz
*Al Ha'aretz* for the land, זו ברכת הארץ Birkat Ha'aretz. *Zu Birkat
Ha'aretz*. Now that by the way is פשט *Pshat*, you know, just
for a minute, which is we tend to focus on the benching
as fundamentally for the food, on the ברכת הזן *Birkat Hazan*. But
the פסוקים psukim, *Psukim* basically say I'm bringing you to this great
land, ארץ aretz הרים ובקעות *Eretz harim u'vekaot* and it has all
these things and you'll eat and you'll be satisfied and you'll thank
God for the great land, על הארץ הטובה al ha'aretz hatova *Al
ha'aretz hatova*. So according to the פסוקים psukim *Psukim* it's fundamentally a
recognition for the land of ישראל *Israel*. So that clearly at least
according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is certain part of the דאורייתא
de'oraita, *De'oraita*, זו ברכת הארץ Birkat Ha'aretz, *Zu Birkat Ha'aretz* one minute.
Now how do you get בונה ירושלים voneh Yerushalayim, *Boneh Yerushalayim* which
is also assumed to be דאורייתא *De'oraita*? הטובה hatovah, זו בונה ירושלים
voneh Yerushalayim *Hatova zu Boneh Yerushalayim*. The good land, what makes it
good? Not just the fruit, what makes it good is it's the
place of the divine presence, is that there's ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and
a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. וכן הוא אומר *Vechein hu
omer*: ההר הטוב הזה והלבנון *Hahar hatov hazeh v'halevanon*,
this good mountain and the Lebanon. So ההר הטוב *Hahar hatov*, what's
the mountain that's good? That is ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*. So therefore the
idea of mentioning ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* is understood what makes it דאורייתא
*De'oraita* is not restoring ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, but understanding that what we're thankful
for is the land, but not just the land that is, you
know, good in the material sense, but a land that is the
place of God's presence, a land that has ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. So now we look forward to
the time when it will be rebuilt, but going back to the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about דוד Dovid, ושלמה *David U'Shlomo*, even when it
was present, acknowledging and thanking that we have such a land that
is part of thanking God for the land. And the last part
of this which is הטוב והמטיב hatov vehametiv *Hatov VeHaMeitiv*, where are
we, אשר נתן לך asher natan lach זו הטוב והמטיב *Asher natan
lach zu Hatov VeHaMeitiv*. So because there was an opinion before which
is largely rejected but there was an opinion that הטוב והמטיב *Hatov
VeHaMeitiv* is דאורייתא *De'oraita* and here it's coming out from אשר נתן
לך *Asher natan lach* that God has given you. So somehow that
means for everything God has given you הטוב והמטיב *Hatov VeHaMeitiv* you
make a ברכה bracha *Bracha* that God does good in all ways,
everything God has given us. הטוב והמטיב *Hatov VeHaMeitiv*, yeah.
This emphasis on the land, does anybody bring up the possibility that
maybe benching is not
דאורייתא *De'oraita* חוץ
לארץ *Chutz la'aretz* or not דאורייתא *De'oraita*?
Yeah, I mean you don't get that sense at all in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, right? The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* discusses דאורייתא *De'oraita*, דאורייתא
*De'oraita*, it's being written in בבל *Bavel* and so on.
Yeah, I don't know if there is anybody that says that. I
could check. I mean obviously פשט הפסוקים *Pshat ha-psukim* could lead you
to that conclusion but in terms of the way it's developed here
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you don't get the sense at all
that they go so far to say that it was not דאורייתא
*De'oraita*. Same way they don't say it's not דאורייתא *De'oraita* they're learning
that you have to mention ירושלים *Yerushalayim* but they're not saying ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* has to be built for it to be דאורייתא *De'oraita*. So
the same way, you know, we can acknowledge the land that God
has given us without us actually having eaten from that land or
being on the land, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* still that the acknowledgment
of it is still דאורייתא *De'oraita* although it is ironic because according
to the פסוקים pesukim *Psukim* it sounds like you actually directly benefit
from the land itself, from the land that God has given you.
משה *Moshe* establishes the הזן *ha-Zan* from the מן *Mann*, which is
outside the land.
Right, right, so according to this, they would not have yet been
יוצא *yotze* the דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*, sort of like the way משה *Moshe*
made the three ערי מקלט *arei miklat* before they were able to
get all six, you know? So we're getting there, okay, we're working
out the stages, we're doing the best we can. Alright, אלו אלא
לאחרב *elu ela l'acharav*. Now the question here of course becomes at
what point is this an אסמכתא *asmachta* or is this literal? Because
now here it's going to be learning the ברכה bracha *bracha* beforehand,
which some גמרות Gmarot *Gemoras* try to make דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*, but in
the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that the ברכות *brachos* beforehand
was only דרבנן *d'Rabanan*. Let's see what this ברייתא *braisa* says here.
אלו אלא לאחרב *elu ela l'acharav*, I only know the idea of
making a blessing after you've eaten. לפניו מניין *lefanav minayin*, how about
before you've eaten? אמרת קל וחומר kal v'chomer, *amarta kal v'chomer*, you
can learn it from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer. *kal v'chomer*. כשהוא
שבע מברך *keshu saveia mevarech*, if he when he's satisfied he makes
a ברכה bracha *bracha*, כשהוא רעב לא כל שכן *keshu ra'ev lo
kol sheken*, all the more so when you're hungry, because then you're
more, you know, you more appreciate what this blessing of food is
because you know you're you know you're more eager for it. Of
course, maybe you haven't experienced it, so you're not directly responding to
the to the experience of the goodness, but at least you're more
appreciative of the goodness.
אין למידין מן הדין *ein l'medin min hadin* doesn't apply to this
to make it דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*? אין למידין מן הדין *ein l'medin min
hadin* is more about like אין עונשין מן הדין *ein onshin min
hadin*, you can't get a punishment, right, איסורים *issurim*. Right, if the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* felt it was a real קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*,
you know, it might have you know stayed as דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* and
there are גמרות *Gemoras* that sound like you know maybe there were
opinions, maybe this תוספתא *Tosefta* really believes it's דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*. There are
sources that sound that way, but the conclusion at least of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we had at the beginning of the sixth פרק
perek *perek* assumed that it was דרבנן *d'Rabanan*. But there are some
sources that seem to want to learn that it is דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*
and not an אסמכתא *asmachta*. Okay, רבי אומר אינו צריך eino tzarich,
*Rebbi omer eino tzarich*. You don't need to learn it from there,
okay, ואכלת ושבעת *v'achalta v'savata* we'll see which what part of אינו
צריך *eino tzarich*. ואכלת ושבעת וברכת זו ברכת הזן *v'achalta v'savata u'beirachta
zu birchas ha-Zan*. אבל ברכת הזימון *aval birchas ha-zimmun*, where do you
get זימון *zimmun* from? את ה' אלהיך וגו' *es Hashem Elokecha v'go*
that's from גדלו לה' אתי *gadlu l'Hashem iti nafka*. That's from the
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* we quoted at the beginning of the of the
פרק *perek*, praise you know raise God with me ונרוממה שמו יחדיו
*u'neromemah shemo yachdav* we'll do it in all together. Now again the
problem with that is that it's not specifically in the context of
of ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon. *birchas hamazon*, okay, and that פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk* by the way גדלו לה' אתי *gadlu l'Hashem iti* is also
learned for the idea of ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah? *birchas ha-Torah*, it's
learned for other things, so it's interesting why רבי *Rebbi* sort of
wants to take it out of a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* at least
because that connecting it to ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon *birchas hamazon*, but
maybe he doesn't believe it's so much פשט *pshat* of the פסוק
*pasuk* that was quoted before. על הארץ זו ברכת הארץ Birkat Ha'aretz
*al ha'aretz zu birchas ha'aretz*, הטובה hatovah, זו בנין ירושלים *ha'tovah zu
binyan Yerushalayim*, וכן הוא אומר ההר הטוב הזה והלבנון v'chen hu omer
hahar hatov hazeh v'halevanon. *v'chen hu omer ha-har ha-tov hazeh v'ha-Levanon*, so
now it's the same for the second and third ברכה bracha *bracha*.
הטוב והמטיב *ha-tov v'ha-meitiv*, but הטוב והמטיב *ha-tov v'ha-meitiv* that's not דאורייתא
*d'Oraisa*, ביבנה תקנוה *b'Yavne tiknuha* that's from יבנה *Yavne*. Okay, so רבי
*Rebbi* argues on two things. Number one, הטוב והמטיב *ha-tov v'ha-meitiv* is
דרבנן *d'Rabanan*. Number two, the זימון *zimmun* is learned from a different
פסוק *pasuk*, maybe that's also trying to say זימון *zimmun* is also
not דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*, which is overwhelmingly the consensus of the ראשונים rishonim
*Rishonim*. Right, so this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes it sound at least
according to one opinion it might be, but overwhelmingly the consensus is
that it's not דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*. So that might be what רבי *Rebbi*
is doing, is a little bit saying it's not all in the
פסוק *pasuk*, okay, some of it is from elsewhere.
And now how about ברכה bracha *bracha* beforehand? אלו אלא לאחרב *elu
ela l'acharav*, לפניו מניין *lefanav minayin*, how do I know beforehand? תלמוד
לומר אשר נתן לך *talmud lomar asher nasan lach*. So what we
what any whatever God has given you, and from there we learn
מי שנתן לך *mi she'nasan lach*, from the moment God has given
it to you, even before you've benefited from it you should make
a ברכה bracha *bracha*. So even though he's saying some things are
not דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* again, if you take this as פשט *pshat*, he's
still insisting that the ברכה bracha *bracha* beforehand is דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* but
from a different place from the פסוק *pasuk*, not a קל וחומר
*kal v'chomer*. רבי יצחק אומר אינו צריך *Rebbi Yitzchak omer eino tzarich*,
you don't need to learn it from there. Let's see what he
disagrees with. הרי הוא אומר Harei hu omer, וברך את לחמך ואת
מימיך *harei hu omer u'beirach es lachmecha v'es meimecha*. So this is
the ברכה bracha *bracha* beforehand, not from אשר נתן לך *asher nasan
lach*, but the ברכה bracha *bracha* that says the פסוק *pasuk* that
says God will bless the your your bread and your water. אל
תקרי וברך *al tikrei u'beirach* God will bless, אלא וברך *ela u'vareich*,
you should bless, you should make a ברכה bracha *bracha* for your
food and your water. ואימתי קרוי לחם *v'eimasai karui lechem*, when is
it called לחם *lechem*? קודם שיאכלנו *kodem she'yochlenu*, before you eat it,
afterwards it's no longer לחם *lechem*. So therefore you see you have
to make a ברכה bracha? *bracha* beforehand. So it's very interesting, who
people are really תנאים *Tannaim* are really attempting to learn one minute
a ברכה bracha ראשונה *bracha rishonah* really seeming to be like they're
trying to make it דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* and not just an אסמכתא *asmachta*.
רבי נתן אומר אינו צריך *Rebbi Nasan omer eino tzarich*, you don't
have to learn it from there, הרי הוא אומר כבואכם העיר *harei
hu omer k'vo'achem ha-ir*. Now we're learning it from a פסוק *pasuk*
by שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, which is clearly taking it away from the
דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* category. So כבואכם העיר *k'vo'achem ha-ir* when you come to
the city, these are some women talking to שאול Shaul *Shaul* who
was looking for שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*, so when you go to the
city כן תמצאון אותו *ken timtza'un oso* you'll find him there בטרם
יעלה הבמה לאכול *b'terem ya'aleh ha-bamah l'echol* before he goes up to
the high to the במה *bamah* לאכול כי לא יאכל העם עד
בואו *l'echol ki lo yochal ha-am ad bo'o*, the people won't eat
until he comes until שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* comes. Again they're talking to
שאול Shaul's *Shaul* who's looking for שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. כי הוא יברך
הזבח *ki hu v'beirach ha-zevach*, he will bless the sacrifice, אחרי כן
יאכלו הקרואים *acharei chen yochlu ha-kru'im*, afterwards they will eat. So you
see, he first has to bless the sacrifice. Right, like some people
think that, okay, you know, something is kosher because a rabbi blesses
it. So here only after שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* blesses it will the
people eat, but the גמרא *Gemara* understands that that blessing is a
blessing for actually you know eating, not Because it's a sacrifice and
a מצוה, mitzvah but it's because of the eating. So again, taking
the idea of a prior ברכה bracha away from being a דאורייתא,
maybe seeing it as an early phenomenon but away from being a
דאורייתא. Now the גמרא digresses and says, וכל כך למה, v'chol kach
lama, why did they have to go on and on and on?
I mean, that's a pretty sort of verbose way of saying, you
know, oh he's over there. So, לפי שנשים דברניות הן, lefi shenashim
davraniot hen, so you'll love this, right, because women are
chatterers. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, so the גמרא doesn't leave it at
that, it gives other opinions. כדי להסתכל ביופיו של שאול, k'dei l'histakel
b'yofyo shel Shaul, שאול Shaul was so handsome that they wanted to
keep on talking to him so they could spend more time looking
at him. דכתיב, d'chtiv, משכמו ומעלה גבוה מכל העם, mishichmo vamala gavoah
mikol ha'am, from his shoulders and above he was higher, taller than
anybody. So anyway, he was obviously very good-looking. That's why they were
talking him up. ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן says,
לפי שאין מלכות נוגעת בחברתה אפילו כמלא נימא. lefi she'ein malchut noga'at
b'chavertah afilu k'mlo nima. It wasn't any problem with the women. It
was that it was שאול's Shaul time to take over for שמואל
and there can, you know, one kingship cannot touch the other, there
can be no overlap. You don't want to incur any incursion into
the other person's sort of period of rulership. So therefore, שאול Shaul
when שאול Shaul's would meet with שמואל, that's when the kingship would,
that's when, שמואל wasn't a king, but that's when שאול Shaul's would
be anointed and the kingship would start. שאול's Shaul rulership would start,
שמואל would pass from the scene, and it wasn't yet the time
for that to happen. So there needed to be a delay until
it was שמואל's time was over and then שאול's time could begin.
So they needed to, you know, to delay him for a few
minutes. I don't know if they knew what they were doing, but
that was the purpose that it served.
כמלא נימא k'mlo nima means by a hair.
Even by a hair, right, so even if it was just a
few minutes, it wasn't yet the time for שאול to take over,
so they had, he had to be delayed.
ומיניה לברכת המזון. u'minei l'Birkat Hamazon. Now, so far we've been discussing
how do you know the ברכה bracha the benching and how do
you know the ברכה bracha beforehand? ברכת התורה מנין? Birkat Hatorah minayin?
How do you know about ברכת התורה? Birkat Hatorah Now interesting that
ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah, is put here. Why is that relevant for
the discussion? So on the one hand, it's relevant because the גמרא
understands that this is the other ברכה which is really understood to
be דאורייתא. Although the conclusion is that the ברכה beforehand is דרבנן,
okay, the ברכת התורה, Birkat Hatorah which is also not clear in
any of the פסוקים, is generally understood to really be a דאורייתא.
There also is a place, if you remember way back in the
more towards the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, that the גמרא wanted
to use ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah as a basis for a ברכה
before, for before eating. It said that the same way you make
a
ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah before learning,
am I remembering correctly? I believe the גמרא said that you should
also make a ברכה on food before eating. I believe what the
גמרא earlier... so it's part of that same discussion. Let me just
see if I remember that correctly.
I'm not talking about public reading, right?
No, not necessarily. I mean sometimes you are, but, yeah, the גמרא
says, מנין לברכת המזון לאחריה מן התורה, minayin l'Birkat Hamazon l'achareha min
haTorah, שנאמר, ואכלת ושבעת וברכת. מנין לברכת התורה לפניה מן התורה, minayin
l'Birkat Hatorah l'faneha min haTorah, שנאמר כי שם ה' אקרא הבו גודל.
shene'emar ki shem Hashem ekra havu godel. So then the גמרא says,
and we should make a
קל וחומר, למדנו ברכת התורה לאחריה מברכת המזון מקל וחומר, lamadnu Birkat
Hatorah l'achareha miBirkat Hamazon mikal v'chomer, ברכת המזון לפניה מברכת התורה מקל
וחומר. Birkat Hamazon l'faneha miBirkat Hatorah mikal v'chomer. So the גמרא wants
to sort of say that ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah comes before, ברכת
המזון Birkat HaMazon. comes after, we should be able to learn one
from the other, and from there derive that the ברכה for food
comes before the same way ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah comes before. And
the ברכה for תורה Torah. comes after, when you do have public
reading, from the idea of ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon comes after. So
in many גמרות the discussion of ברכת התורה Birkat Hatorah and ברכת
המזון Birkat HaMazon and ברכה before are in the same conversation, either
to use them as models for one another, or because of the
assumption that ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah. is also the one biblical ברכה
in addition to ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon. Just one minute. So the
גמרא continues, מנין,
so how do I know ברכת התורה מנין? Birkat Hatorah minayin? אמר
רב שמואל קל וחומר. Amar Rav Shmuel kal v'chomer. It's a קל
וחומר. החיי שעה מברך החיי עולם הבא לא כל שכן? hachayei sha'ah
mivarech hachayei olam haba lo kol sheken? If you bless for things
that give you sustenance in this world, how much more so should
you make a blessing for things that give you sustenance in the
world to come? Now, of course, that's true in a, you know,
from an intellectual perspective. From an immediate experiential perspective, there's obviously a
difference, so that's questionable if that really is the basis. And if
it were the basis, that would indicate more of a ברכה after
you learn, right, not before you learn, if we're going to use
ברכת המזון Birkat HaMazon as the model. רבי חייא בר נחמני תלמידו
של רבי ישמעאל אומר משמו של רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Chiya bar Nachmani
talmido shel Rabbi Yishmael omer mishmo shel Rabbi Yishmael, so the other
statement in the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is, אינו צריך,
that's not what it's based on. הרי הוא אומר, על הארץ הטובה
אשר נתן לך, al ha'aretz hatova asher natan lach, the good land
God has given you. ולהלן הוא אומר, u'l'halan hu omer, ואתנה לך
לוחות האבן התורה והמצוה, v'etna lacha luchot ha'even hatorah v'hamitzvah, I've also
given you the תורה. Torah. So if we thank God for the
land, we thank God for the תורה. Torah So conceptually it's the
same idea, we thank God for what God has given us, but
we learn it more from the פסוקים rather than from an analogy.
Again, that would more indicate a ברכה maybe after the fact, or
at least a ברכה of thanksgiving.
רבי מאיר אומר מנין כשם ש. Rabbi Meir omer minayin k'shem she.
is the earlier גמרא, which is the ברכה our פרק quoted about
זימון. כי שם ה' אקרא הבו גדל לאלהינו. Ki shem Hashem ekra
havu godel leloheinu. When I call out God's name, when a תורה
Torah? which proclaims God's revelation, you have to sort of acknowledge it
and give greatness to God. It raises questions how we conceptualize ברכת
התורה. Birkat HaTorah According to this, ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah is fundamentally
conceptualized as a blessing of thanks, thanks or praise similar to the
benching of to ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon, Okay, similar הבו גדל, havu
godel, the difference between the הבו גדל havu godel פסוק and the
ברכת המזון is הבו גדל havu godel is more like praise and
the ברכת המזון model is more like thanks. Although those are related,
clearly there is a different subtle difference between thanks and praise. So
those are two different similar but subtly different as we know ברכת
התורה Birkat HaTorah also has a has a ברכת המצוה Birkat Hamitzvah
component. אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לעסוק בדברי תורה. asher kidshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu
la'asok be'divrei torah. Okay, but generally the ראשונים rishonim understand that ברכת
התורה Birkat HaTorah is דאורייתא is much more in the thanks and
the praise category than in the ברכת המצוה Birkat Hamitzvah category, learned
either from כי שם ה' אקרא or learned from the אשר נתן
לך and the analogy to the ברכת המזון. You've been waiting to
ask, Simon.
So my question is, this seems to be focusing on the subjective
experience of being stated, satiated, right? So let's say you ate past
שובע sova or like you ate and then it made you sick.
Right. Would you still have to do a ברכה?
No, so that also the same way, yeah, I mean according to
דאורייתא is when is when you're satiated. If you're not, then it's
not דאורייתא, but okay, so that's true, but דרבנן you might still
be the same way you are by כזית. Okay.
Yes. Conceptualizing the ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah more as an act of
gratitude rather than as a recognition of fulfillment of an obligation, is
that in your opinion related to two different ways of conceptualizing קריאת
התורה Kriat HaTorah either as מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai or
learning תורה? Torah Learning תורה Torah, model is more of a חיוב.
chiyuv. The experiential component might be related to the conceptualization of the
blessings themselves.
Right, that's a beautiful idea and it is true that when you
make the ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah for the public reading, you don't
say the אשר קדשנו, asher kidshanu, you only say the as the
other ברכות. Yeah, I wasn't thinking about that, that's an excellent point
and it
seems like it lines up,
it might line up very nicely. I mean those ראשונים that you
that say that they take it seriously that ברכת התורה Birkat HaTorah,
is דאורייתא, obviously don't say specifically in the context of a public
reading of the תורה, Torah they would say like every time, every
time you wake up in the morning or you say it, you're
about to encounter God's תורה Torah, and giving thanks and acknowledgment for
that תורה, Torah? but you're absolutely correct that the saying of it
at the public קריאת התורה Kriat HaTorah does not have the ברכת
המצוה Birkat Hamitzvah component and it does relate more to that experiential.
If that's the case, then why don't we say a ברכה after
we learn תורה?
Torah Yeah, because so right, because the idea of, well as we
just said, in some ways when you say before, it's more when
you're anticipating and appreciating and so on, but the after has the
benefit that you actually sort of experienced the benefit. Now of course
you could say by תורה Torah. you also experienced the intellectual, the
spiritual benefit, but in some ways the the that is it's a
good question. There's no שובע sova meaning the same sort of degree
of of sort of of immediate experience, you know, of a bodily
pleasure and experience is not the same, but it could be that's
why you do the ברכה after in the public קריאת התורה Kriat
HaTorah and the גמרא earlier didn't want to learn from the model
of ברכת המזון for the ברכה after as well. But certainly one
difference is that sense of sort of of immediate experiential sort of
pleasure, you know, it's more the intellectual understanding of what it all
means than the direct sort of pleasure that was achieved from it.
Depends how good your learning was, whether it was pleasurable.
And also the more you learn the hungrier you get. Oh, but
could it also be that there's no end, when would you say
it?
Well, that could, that's a good point as well. Yeah, that that
that could be as well. And maybe for the קריאת התורה Kriat
HaTorah where there's a clear endpoint, that's a good point as well.
Okay, so let's as the גמרא continues. Now, we discussed before a
little bit about the מברך על הרעה, mevarech al hara, so I
said הטוב והמטיב was recognizing the good even when things are not
ideal and when things are bad, but now the גמרא shifts to
the direct מברך על הרעה. mevarech al hara. So, רבי נהוראי אומר
מנין כשם שמברך על הטובה כך מברך על הרעה. Rabbi Nehorai omer
minayin keshem shemevarech al hatovah kach mevarech al hara. So the broach
now where they have been, how do we know sort of what's
the source of various institutions of blessings, like particular ברכת המזון, ברכת
הנהנין, Birkat HaNehenin, ברכת התורה, Birchas HaTorah here he talks about like
all basically theological point. Where do we understand this idea or general
sort of, you know, concept about when is it appropriate to make
benching, do you make on the we bless God, recognize God even
for the even for the bad, the same way you bless for
the good you bless for the bad. תלמוד לומר אשר נתן לך
ה' אלהיך, Talmud lomar asher natan lach Hashem elokecha, as God has
given you, whatever God gives you. דיינך בכל דין שדנך, Dayanecha bechol
din shedanecha, the way God has judged you, any way God has
judged you, בין מדה טובה בין מדת פורענות, bein midah tovah bein
midat puranut, whether it is good, whether it is bad, whatever God
has given you, you acknowledge, you acknowledge that it is all part
of God's plan. Like, you know, what is it? You get what
you get and you don't get upset. So, okay, so that's where.
Whatever God has given you, it's all coming from God, and somehow
we see that it's all part of God's plan. I have to
share with you a beautiful שפת אמת Sfas Emes I happened to
be reading over ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, which he sort of said,
the idea that this is a, that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is
a
יום הדין, Yom HaDin, and so he's sort of dealing with the
question is it יום הדין, Yom HaDin, is it רחמים? Rachamim? We
sort of want the מדת הדין middas hadin to be הופך hofech
to מדת הרחמים. middas harachamim. And he says the way the דין
din becomes רחמים rachamim is when we acknowledge
the fact that we're able to present ourselves לדין ledin and we
see that this is actually an, it's a good thing that we
are in this relationship with God and that we're, and that God's
in position to sort of, God cares about, I mean sort of
elaborating a little bit, but he basically says that God judges the
whole world. What makes it רחמים rachamim and not דין din is
when you accept the responsibility for that process and when you position,
put yourself in front of God for דין din and you acknowledge
that it is because of God's care for you and your relationship
with God that God has come to judge you. And when you
come with it with that approach, then that changes the whole relationship.
Then it's a relationship of care and concern and love, and it's
a relationship of רחמים rachamim and it's not a relationship of דין.
din. So, anyway, that's his, anyway, just thought a little bit relevant
to this idea that if you could see the bad things, do
you see them as bad or do you ultimately see them as
part of a relationship and even when bad things happen, that's sort
of an expressive of a loving relationship.
Okay, so now the גמרא says,
where were we? Okay, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר אינו צריך הרי
הוא אומר טובה, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira omer eino tzarich harei hu
omer tovah, the good land, הטובה, and then the good, the good
land. טובה זו תורה, Tovah zu Torah, טובה tovah is good, what's
good? It's תורה. Torah וכן הוא אומר כי לקח טוב נתתי לכם.
v'chen hu omer ki lekach tov nasati lachem. הטובה זו בניין ירושלים.
Hatovah zu binyan Yerushalayim. וכן הוא אומר ההר הטוב הזה והלבנון. So
he's not dealing with מדה טובה מדה פורעניות, middah tovah middah puraniyos,
he's going back to ברכת התורה and you get it from the
word טובה, tovah, it is what is
good. תניא רבי אליעזר אומר. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer. Now that was
the basic source of these institutions. Now we're going to get to
the text of the ברכות. רבי אליעזר אומר כל שלא אמר ארץ
חמדה טובה ורחבה בברכת הארץ, Rabbi Eliezer omer kol shelo amar eretz
chemdah tovah u'rechavah b'birchas ha'aretz, if you didn't really emphasize how good
the land was, right, ארץ חמדה טובה ורחבה, eretz chemdah tovah u'rechavah,
ומלכות בית דוד בבונה ירושלים, u'malchus Beis Dovid b'bonei Yerushalayim, and if
you only mentioned ירושלים but you didn't mention דוד's kingship, לא יצא
ידי חובתו. lo yatza yedei chovaso. Now you didn't fulfill your obligation,
which is pretty amazing. Now does that mean literally you didn't fulfill?
Is it an exaggeration? Does it mean biblically? Does it mean rabbinically?
I mean all we know from the תורה Torah. is הארץ and
הטובה, but somehow he's saying that to say it's a really good
land you have to really underscore it and emphasize the good of
ירושלים, it's not just the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's also מלכות
בית דוד malchus Beis Dovid is part of that. So,
this is now expanding on what are the necessary themes that are
part of the בנשן. benschen. Okay? And רש"י Rashi says שעליו נתקדשה
ירושלים, she'al yado niskadsha Yerushalayim, that through דוד, ירושלים became sanctified, so
it still focuses on the בית המקדש, but you could have shifted
it, it's not just about the בית המקדש, it's about Jewish sovereignty
is also part of it and it's really a slightly different theme.
Okay. נחום הזקן אומר, Nachum Hazaken omer, נחום Nachum the elder says,
שצריך שיזכור בה ברית, she'tzarich she'yizkor bah bris, it's not enough
to say the land, you have to mention the covenant God has
given us because the covenant is the basis for which we have
inherited the land. Now that ברית bris does not mean ברית מילה,
bris milah, that means the ברית bris with the land. רש"י Rashi
says, right, but the גמרא is going to soon move into the
ברית מילה. bris milah.
Because within the פרשה, parsha, ברית מילה bris milah anyway it says,
if you look, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, it says ונתתי לך
ולזרעך אחריך את ארץ מגוריך את כל ארץ כנען, v'nasati lecha u'l'zaracha
acharecha es eretz megurecha es kol eretz Kena'an, right? So leading up
to the מצוה of the ברית מילה bris milah is this idea
of the ברית bris of the land. But until now anyway it
could be understood as the ברית bris of the land. We're going
to keep on, we're going to develop that. רבי יוסי אומר צריך
שיזכור בה תורה, Rabbi Yosi omer tzarich she'yizkor bah Torah, you have
to mention תורה. Torah Where's תורה Torah, relevant? So if you look
at רש"י he says, רש"י says שצריך שיזכור בה תורה שאף בזכות
התורה והמצוה ירשוה שנאמר למען תחיו ורביתם ובאתם וירשתם את הארץ. she'tzarich
she'yizkor bah Torah she'af bizchus haTorah v'hamitzvah yarshuah shene'emar lema'an tichyu u'rvitem
u'vasem v'yirashtem es ha'aretz. If you've been paying attention as we've been
reading ספר דברים, Sefer Devarim, the recurring theme of ספר דברים Sefer
Devarim is you're getting the land because you're doing the מצוות. mitzvos.
And if you don't do the מצוות, mitzvos, you get kicked out
of the land. So within the context of the significance of the
land is that the land is part of a covenant and the
land, what makes us live on the land, is the learning of
the תורה, Torah, and all of that is part of our relationship
to the land. פלימו אומר, Plimo omer, פלימו Plimo says, צריך שיקדים
ברית לתורה, tzarich she'yakdim bris l'Torah, you have to mention ברית bris
before the תורה, Torah שזו ניתנה בשלוש בריתות, she'zu nitna b'shalosh britos,
תורה Torah, was given three times. It was given in הר סיני
Har Sinai with the ברית, bris, it was given at ערבות מואב,
Arvos Moav, מלבד הברית אשר כרתי אתם בחורב, milvad habris asher karati
itam b'chorev, and it was given again when they crossed the ירדן.
Yarden. וזו, v'zu, ברית, bris, now we're switching to ברית מילה, bris
milah, ניתנה בי"ג בריתות. nitna b'yud gimmel britos. It says ברית bris
thirteen times in the פרשה parsha of ברית מילה. bris milah. So
now we're no longer just about the ברית. bris. of the land,
we're on ברית מילה. Bris Milah. And that's going to raise questions
relating to women as we're going to see very soon. רבי אבא
אומר Rabbi Abba omer צריך שיאמר בו הודאה תחילה וסוף. tzarich sheyomar
bo hoda'ah techila v'sof. You have to say thanks at the beginning
and the end. We're still in the ברכת הארץ. All of this
notice besides that mention of מלכות בית דוד Malchut Beit David is
all about the land. What is the context of the land? The
land through a ברית, bris, the land through תורה, Torah and now
the land is so much about thanking God for the land that
it has to begin with thanking and ending with thanking. נודה לך,
Nodeh lecha, you start with thanking and you end right with you
know, רש"י says what's the end of... ועל כולם ה' אלוהינו אנחנו
מודים לך. V'al kulam Hashem Elokeinu anachnu modim lach. So you once
again underscore the gratitude and the thankfulness. והפוחת Vehapocheit לא יפחות מאחת.
lo yifchos me'achat. And if you say if פוחת, pocheit, excuse me,
if you say a minimum amount of praise it should be no
fewer than one. It's hard to be less than one, and it's
not clear what does he mean? Does he mean ארץ חמדה טובה
ורחבה? Eretz chemda tova u'rechava? Does he mean those adjectives? Does he
mean things we haven't been mentioning until now? Anyway וכל הפוחת מאחת
v'chol hapocheit me'achat if you do fewer than one, whatever the one
of, הרי זה מגונה harei zeh meguneh that is unseemly or not
correct. וכל החותם V'chol hachoteim now what should the חתימה chatima of
the ברכה be? If your חתימה chatima is מנחיל ארצות Manchil Aratzot
בברכת הארץ b'virkat ha'aretz not על הארץ הטובה or על הארץ ועל
המזון al ha'aretz v'al hamazon but God who bequeaths lands in the
plural, ומושיע את ישראל בבונה ירושלים u'moshia et Yisrael b'voneh Yerushalayim or
redeems the Jewish people in בונה ירושלים, voneh Yerushalayim הרי זה בור,
harei zeh bur, an ignoramus. Now that's pretty heavy, but by the
way what we do see from this and we're going to see
a little bit later is that some people actually did have that
חתימה. chatima. Some אמוראים Amoraim which he's now calling a בור bur
actually did have that חתימה. chatima. What could be the first of
all one thing you see is that the liturgy wasn't fixed and
you see this a lot. You know they'll say you have to
have this point and that point but they're not giving word for
word the text. There was a certain you know there was a
certain fluidity there was a certain different versions of it within the
text and therefore some people actually you're not going to say you're
an ignoramus unless some people are actually doing it and you don't
approve. Okay now why are people doing מנחיל ארצות? Manchil Aratzot? It
might be because of this exilic you know גלות galus no but
this גלות galus problem. How do we say על הארץ ועל המזון
al ha'aretz v'al hamazon
if we're not in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? How are we thanking
God for sustenance we had not from ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? So
maybe you want to abstract it. God bequeaths lands to all people.
The first רש"י in בראשית. Bereishit. Right sorry and כוח מעשיו הגיד
לעמו.
Koach ma'asav higid l'amo.
It's an authentic idea in terms of his father he said that
the gentiles shouldn't say that this is no longer your land God
takes land and gives land and has title ultimately.
Right, so all the land is from God, exactly. And therefore maybe
it maybe we can focus on all the land and it all
comes from God and ארץ doesn't mean ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
it doesn't have to for us it mean whatever land this comes
from. But obviously he did not like that because it has to
retain the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael focus and that's the sense of
the פסוק. And that seems to be what the ארצות Aratzot was
about. Now מושיע ישראל Moshia Yisrael instead of בונה ירושלים you could
also imagine if you're in גלות galus maybe before you worry about
בונה ירושלים the first thing you worry about is being redeemed from
גלות. galus. So these could reflect a way in which maybe the
נוסחאות nuscha'ot were being changed from how the גמרא saw them as
original in the פסוק or the themes original to the פסוקים based
on the גלות galus reality. But he did not like it. הרי
זה בור. Harei zeh bur. וכל שאינו אומר ברית ותורה בברכת הארץ
V'chol she'eino omer bris v'Torah b'virkat ha'aretz and if you don't say
the things we've just been saying ברית bris and תורה Torah in
the ברכת הארץ, which is the context which we have the land.
Now the way by the way you certainly understand ברית bris and
תורה for the ברכת הארץ because you want to underscore it about
the relationship to the land of Israel. Okay ומלכות בית דוד בבונה
ירושלים u'malchut Beit David b'voneh Yerushalayim and if you don't say those
things לא יצא ידי חובתו, lo yatza yedei chovato, you did not
fulfill. Again does that mean biblically does it mean rabbinically but now
we're not just saying you have to say it we're saying if
you didn't you weren't יוצא. We'll just read one more
line. מסייע ליה לרבי אלעזר Mesayei lei l'Rabbi Elazar this supports רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar דאמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יעקב בר אחא משום
רבנו d'amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha mishum Rabbeinu כל
שלא אמר ברית ותורה בברכת הארץ ומלכות בית דוד בבונה ירושלים לא
יצא ידי חובתו. kol shelo amar bris v'Torah b'virkat ha'aretz u'malchut Beit
David b'voneh Yerushalayim lo yatza yedei chovato. If you didn't do it
you didn't fulfill your obligation. Again biblical rabbinic it's not clear and
we will continue with this
tomorrow.